"Can Diet and Lifestyle Changes Boost Our GLP-1
Like Ozempic (Semaglutide) Does?"
I’ve talked about the upsides
of pharmacologically boosting
GLP-1 activity
in terms of weight loss,
given the ravages of obesity,
and I’ve also discussed
its downsides,
including common
gastrointestinal reactions
and muscle loss,
as well as the rarer
and more speculative
side effects
such as thyroid cancer,
pancreatitis,
and pancreatic cancer.
And I’ve summarized
the cost-benefit trade-off,
detailing for whom the benefits
may far outweigh the risks,
at least in the short term.
But is there any way
to get the benefits of GLP-1
without the risks,
by boosting it naturally
with diet and lifestyle changes?
Well, there’s exercise.
It appears
to acutely increase GLP-1.
There have been five studies
of exercise and GLP-1,
and four out of five of them
found higher concentrations
of total GLP-1
after High Intensity
Interval Training
and Sprint Interval Training
as well as Moderate Intensity
Continuous Training,
with no apparent difference
between High Intensity Interval
and Moderate Intensity
Continuous.
Compared to control groups
where the study subjects
didn’t exercise at all,
both types of physical activity
(High Intensity Interval and
Moderate Intensity Continuous)
induced significantly higher
GLP-1 concentrations
immediately after exercise,
and 30-90 minutes later.
Unfortunately, there appeared
to be publication bias,
meaning some trials
that failed to show an effect
may have been quietly shelved,
thereby skewing the results.
But what’s the downside
of exercising?
The evidence is overwhelming
that nearly everyone
can benefit
from becoming
more physically active.
What about diet?
There are a variety
of natural products,
foods, beverages, and spices,
that have been shown to boost
our own natural GLP-1 levels.
But can endogenous GLP-1,
meaning GLP-1
from inside the body,
work as an alternative
to the drugs that mimic GLP-1,
like Ozempic?
If you haven’t yet,
I recommend watching
or re-watching my video
about what GLP-1 is
and how it works,
to best fully grasp
the issue at hand.
Our natural GLP-1 levels
rise and fall
in response to meal ingestion.
When we take
these drugs, though,
levels in our blood remain
relatively constant, and high.
But "high" here
is a bit of an understatement.
The total concentration
of these GLP-1 lookalike drugs
in our bloodstream
is typically around
20-30 nanomoles per liter.
Okay, here’s how much GLP-1
rises naturally
in our bloodstream
in the two hours
after we eat a meal,
up to maybe 20 or 30 picomoles.
"Nano-" means billionth;
"pico-" means trillionth.
So, at this scale,
drug levels are up
to like 25,000.
How could
boosting natural levels
even come close?
Well, part of the discrepancy
may be an artifact
of taking blood
from people’s veins
to do blood tests.
Since natural GLP-1
is rapidly deactivated
by an enzyme in our blood,
by the time GLP-1
is secreted by our gut,
makes it through our liver,
heart, and lungs,
then out into our arteries,
only to later reach the veins
where the lab tech
is pulling out blood,
the levels we see are lower
than the arterial levels
that GLP-1 receptors
are exposed to
throughout our body,
though only
by a relatively small amount.
But how do drugs like Ozempic
sit around in the body
for weeks instead of minutes?
They are chemically modified
to stick to the most abundant
protein in our blood.
So, even though the total
drug level in our blood
is up in the nanomolar range,
it’s so tightly bound to protein
that the active level
in our blood
that’s free to actually interact
with tissue receptors
is like a hundred times smaller,
at least down
in the picomolar range.
Thus, although at first glance,
it appears
that plasma drug levels
are extremely high,
they actually may be closer
to those of natural GLP-1 levels
after strong stimulation.
But still, there seems
to be a huge discrepancy.
It’s GLP-1 activation
in the brain
that appears to account for
the regulation of food intake,
but it isn’t currently clear
how this might be related
to GLP-1 in the blood.
The primary source
of GLP-1 secretion
in the body is the gut.
So, wouldn’t it get eaten up
by enzymes in the blood
before much of it
even made it into the brain?
It can cross
the blood-brain barrier,
but is enough
really getting up there?
Well, GLP-1 is also produced
by nerves
in the brainstem itself,
and a large body of evidence
points to
the appetite-reducing effects
of GLP-1 mimicking drugs,
like Ozempic,
being mediated by
these brain GLP-1 receptors.
So, how could
natural blood levels,
expected after
dietary interventions,
aiming to increase
the secretion of gut GLP-1
still have
clinically relevant effects?
Yes, the GLP-1 released
from our intestinal cells
is rapidly degraded,
leading to low systemic levels,
but its effects
appear to be mediated
by vagus nerve stimulation.
The vagus nerve
connects the gut
straight up
into the brainstem,
so it’s directly wired
to the brain
and doesn’t have to rely
on blood transport.
But wait, there are GLP-1
receptors on the pancreas,
the kidneys,
the liver, and the heart.
Why would the body
have GLP-1 receptors
on our peripheral organs,
if the hormone acts mainly
through the vagus nerve?
It’s possible
that strong stimuli
can boost levels
high enough in the blood
to activate
these peripheral receptors.
So, perhaps,
the way GLP-1 normally works
is that we eat a meal,
and GLP-1 sends
the appetite reducing signal
to our brain directly
through the vagus nerve,
and then, our brain
relays the messages
to the relevant systems
throughout the body.
Injecting people
with high levels
of a GLP-1-mimicking drug,
like Ozempic,
means it can circulate
directly through the bloodstream
to all these organs,
including the brain,
and a strong
dietary GLP-1 stimulus
might be able to do both.
But you can’t really know
whether natural,
physiological levels of GLP-1
can suppress appetite,
until you...
put it to the test.
When different levels of GLP-1
are dripped
straight into people’s veins,
you can see
a dose-dependent reduction
in both hunger and food intake.
Okay, but effective doses
used in infusion studies
quadrupled baseline levels
or more,
whereas the blood levels
increased by
GLP-1-boosting foods
tended to only double
baseline levels.
So, while high-dose
GLP-1 infusion
drives a clear change
in hunger and eating behaviors,
is it possible
that inducing GLP-1 secretion
through diet may not?
Well, remember how food
naturally only boosts
blood levels up around 20?
It turns out you can get
a significant drop
in food intake
up to 30-35% less
of an all-you-can-eat meal
simply by getting your GLP-1
levels up to 10 or 15,
or even just 5!
That is well within
doable dietary ranges.
So, while low natural levels
might appear to have
little effect at first glance,
a slight increase in levels
by dietary manipulation
of GLP-1 secretion
could be sufficient
to have clinical relevance.
Thus, we don’t have to strive
for levels comparable to those
obtained using drugs.
And, of course,
this makes sense, right?
Why would our body
naturally produce
an appetite-suppressing hormone
in response to food,
if it didn’t end up
suppressing our appetite?